A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Humanities and the Arts, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Wilson McNeil Lowry FA582
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Humanities and the Arts, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Wilson McNeil Lowry
1952-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lowry, Wilson McNeil Lowry
Ford Foundation
FA582
10.45 Cubic Feet 27 Hollinger document boxes
Wilson McNeil Lowry joined the Ford Foundation in 1953 as Program Director of Education. Mr. Lowry helped develop the Foundation's nascent program in the Humanities and the Arts and served as its first Director when the program was formally established in 1957. He later went on to serve as Vice President of the Office of Policy and Planning (1964-1966), Vice President of the Division of Humanities and the Arts (1965-1975), and Acting President of the Foundation (1965- 1966). He retired in 1975. The Office Files of Wilson McNeil Lowry document his oversight of numerous Ford Foundation programs, including Administration (ADMIN), Education (ED), Economic Development Administration (EDA), Fund for Adult Education (FAE), Humanities and the Arts (HA), International Affairs (IA), International Training and Research (ITR), Overseas Development (OD), Public Affairs (PA), Policy and Planning (PP), Population (POP), Science and Engineering (SE), and Special Projects (SPE). These Program Files make up the bulk of the collection. There are also files on the activities of the Board of Trustees as well as on the planning of the new Ford Foundation building in New York, the Building Committee, and the dedication ceremony in 1967. The files also include documents prepared or assembled by his staff, for example, on the Travel Study Award Program, and records of site visits to Arts and Humanities Program grantees and potential grantees. Of particular note in the collection are the extensive records of the Ford Foundation's involvement with and financial support for the McCone Commission investigation of the 1965 Los Angeles Watts Riots.
Biographical / Historical
Wilson McNeil Lowry (1913-1993) was born on February 17, 1913 in Columbus, Kansas. He graduated from the University of Illinois with a B.A. in 1934 and taught in the University's Department of English from 1936 to 1941 when he received a PhD in English from the University. After service as a Navy lieutenant in World War II, Mr. Lowry worked in journalism, first as Associate Editor of the Dayton Daily News (1946-1947), then Chief of the Washington Bureau of James M. Cox Newspapers (1947-1952). He was Associate Director of the International Press Institute (1952-1953) when he was hired by the Ford Foundation as an assistant to William McPeak in order to direct the Foundation's education program. Mr. Lowry helped develop the Foundation's program in the area of Humanities and the Arts, and served as its first director when the program was formally established in 1957. He later served as Vice President of the Office of Policy and Planning (1964-1966), Vice President of the Division of Humanities and the Arts (1965-1975) and Acting President of the Foundation for a short time after the retirement of Henry T. Heald, until McGeorge Bundy was hired (1965-1966). Mr. Lowry retired in 1975, but continued to work as a pro bono consultant in the arts, including a term as president of the San Francisco Ballet (1988-1991). He died on June 6, 1993.
Biographical / Historical
The Office of the Arts originated as the Office of Humanities and the Arts, created in 1957 under the direction of its first Vice President, Wilson McNeil Lowry. In 1979, the Office of the Arts became a program area under Education and Public Policy, and after the 1997 reorganization, became part of Education, Media, Arts and Culture. Education, Media, Arts and Culture became the Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom Program in 2002.
Arrangement
Arranged into 5 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Board of Trustees, 1954-1972, bulk 1966
Series II. Building-Related Files, 1963-1968
Series III. Grant-Related Files, 1959-1966
Series IV. Programs, 1952-1971
Series V. Speeches and Writings, 1955-1974
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Wilson McNeil Lowry document his participation in and oversight of several Ford Foundation programs and departments. Mr. Lowry also served on the Board of Trustees and his files consist of the policies and procedures developed for and used by the Ford Foundation following the re-establishment of the Foundation in New York City. The files also include documents prepared or assembled by Mr. Lowry's staff, e.g., on the Travel Study Award Program. There are also records of visits to grantees and potential grantees in the field of Arts and Humanities. Of particular note are the extensive records of the Ford Foundation's involvement with and financial support for the McCone Commission investigation of the 1965 Los Angeles Watts Riots.
Separated Materials
Four dictation disks on the University of Wisconsin Urban Extension Program, dated 1/2/1963 and six reel-to-reel audio recordings of Mr. Lowry's speech at the Studio Arena Theatre Conference, 1967, have been separated and stored in Box 47480. A partial transcription of Mr. Lowry speaking at the Buffalo Studio Area Theatre Conference on 4/21/1967 has been tentatively associated with the reel-to-reel audio tapes and is available in Series V. Speeches and Writings of this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Related Materials
The University Archives of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign holds the W. McNeil Lowry Papers, 1941-1993, among their Alumni records. A more complete description of the collection and access requirements may be found online at the University Archives website.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Completion of a use agreement is required prior to providing scholarly access. See RAC Head of Reference (or applicable designee) for details.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
- Board of Trustees, 1954-1972, bulk 1966; 1966; I
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The files primarily are composed of docket files for Board of Trustees meetings and contain grant proposals and memoranda concerning the viability of the proposals. There are also a few discussion papers about subjects brought before the board, such as the College Investment Trust (1954-1967), and related correspondence.
  - College Investment Trust, 1954 May 26-1967 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Approved Budgets, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Foundation Finances, Staff, Grants and Grantmaking Policies, etc., 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda Re: Board Meeting Discussion Items, 1959 November 11- 1966 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Henry Ford Hospital Proposal, 1961 May 22-1964 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Grants to Harvard University -- Proposal Initiated Through John J. McCloy, 1962 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sabbaticals for High School Teachers -- Proposal Initiated Through John J. McCloy, 1962 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda Relating To or Initiated Through Board Members, 1963 January 11-1966 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Warren Weaver Correspondence Re: Salk Institute for Biological Studies Proposal, 1963 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Warren Weaver Correspondence Re: Book on Philanthropy, 1964 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Charles E. Wyzanski Jr. Correspondence Re: Medical School Proposal, 1964 February 6-14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bethuel M. Webster's Trip to England, Denmark and Finland, 1964 August 4-September 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Henry T. Heald Retirement, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- Education, 1966 February 2-March 30 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- Economic Development Administration, 1966 February 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- General, 1966 January 5-February 11 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- Humanities and the Arts, 1966 February 2-9 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- International Affairs, 1965 December 31-1966 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- International Training and Research, 1966 January 19-February 8 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- Public Affairs, 1966 January 26-February 17 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- Population, 1966 February 4 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- Science and Engineering, 1966 January 20-February 10 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Docket, March 1966 -- Special Programs, 1966 January 26-February 9 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Education, 1966 May 5-27 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Economic Development Administration, 1966 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- General, 1966 April 15-May 20 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Humanities and the Arts, 1966 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- International Affairs, 1966 April 11-May 20 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- International Training and Research, 1966 May 9-19 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Public Affairs (1 of 2), 1966 May 13-June 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Public Affairs (2 of 2), 1966 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Population, 1966 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Science and Engineering, 1966 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Docket, June 1966 -- Special Programs, 1966 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- Education, 1966 May 19-August 24 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- General, 1966 August 15 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- Humanities and the Arts, 1966 August 11-25 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- International Affairs, 1966 July 11-August 12 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- Overseas Development, 1966 August 8-25 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- Population, 1966 August 11 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- Science and Engineering, 1966 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Docket, September 1966 -- Special Programs, 1966 July 20-26 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- Education, 1966 October 31 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- Economic Development Administration, 1966 November 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- International Affairs, 1966 October 12-31 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- International Training and Research, 1966 November 7 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- National Affairs/Resources and the Environment, 1966 October 31 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- Overseas Development, 1966 November 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- Population, 1966 October 28 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- Public Affairs, 1966 August 26-November 11 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Docket, December 1966 -- Special Programs, 1966 October 31 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Forecasting and Financial Policy of the Ford Foundation, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General Memoranda, 1966 May 25 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Possible New Trustees -- Memorandum, Biographies, 1966 May 25-26 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Travel and Study Award Program, 1967 January 27-1970 July 23 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Individual Award Programs: A Brief Survey", 1967 January (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Dependent Organizations" -- Paper/List of Organizations Receiving Foundation Support, 1970 December (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Dependent Organizations -- Memoranda, Notes, Paper Draft, 1971 July 30-September 3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Ford Foundation and "Dependent" Organizations, 1971 September 16 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Humanities and the Arts (HA) Discussion Papers, 1972 May 24-June 2 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Building-Related Files, 1963-1968; II
  These three files contain information on the Ford Foundation building, the Building Committee, and the dedication ceremony in 1967. Included is planning information about the Foundation's move into the building and floor plans detailing where each department was relocating. The specific offices into which Foundation executives such as Mr. Lowry moved are also identified.
  - 320 East 43rd Street -- Memoranda, Articles, Press Clippings Re: Move to and Uses of New Building, 1967 April 12-1968 July 23 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Building Committee, 1963 June 18-1967 August 7 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation Building Dedication -- Memorandum, Invitations, Programs, 1967 December 1-1968 March 28 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Grant-Related Files, 1959-1966; III
  The files consist of a few grant requests with accompanying memoranda for the Education, Humanities and the Arts, Overseas Development, Population and Public Affairs programs.
  - Education -- The Fund For the Advancement of Education, 1963 February 25-1966 June 23 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Humanities and the Arts -- Grants-in-Aid Programs, 1964 October 29 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Humanities and the Arts -- Grant Requests, 1963 May 14-1966 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Humanities and the Arts -- Independent Art Schools, 1966 June 14 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Humanities and the Arts -- Program for Orchestras, 1966 February 11-June 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Overseas Development -- Grant Requests and Discussion Memoranda, 1963 March 22-1966 September 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Overseas Development -- Middle East and Africa (MEA) Grant Requests, 1962 December 26-1965 July 22 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Overseas Development -- South and Southeast Asia (SSEA) Grant Requests, 1962 December 27-1965 July 22 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Population - Grant Requests and Grant Summaries, 1964 May 13-1965 May 6 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Public Affairs - Grant Requests, 1959-1966 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Programs, 1952-1971; IV
  The files have been arranged alphabetically by program area and then by chronological order.
  Correspondence, memoranda, evaluations and reports from specific program areas have been arranged by program area: Administration (ADMIN), Education (ED), Economic Development Administration (EDA), Fund for Adult Education (FAE), Humanities and the Arts (HA), International Affairs (IA), International Training and Research (ITR), Overseas Development (OD), Public Affairs (PA), Policy and Planning (PP), Population (POP), Science and Engineering (SE), and Special Projects (SPE). Staff memoranda, reports, and correspondence that concern more than one program area or cannot be clearly identified as having originated from a specific program have been filed before the clearly identified program materials.
  The largest sets of files are for Education and Policy and Planning, indicative of Mr. Lowry's several years of oversight. Of particular note are the extensive Policy and Planning files concerning the issue of "Negro education" and the Foundation's Urban Extension Programs at various universities. The Public Affairs files reveal the Foundation's support for the investigation of the 1965 Watts riots in Los Angeles. The Science and Engineering folder on Conservation (1962-1965) represents the Foundation's work in conservation and the environment, which would become a new program area in 1966, and includes a federal task force report entitled "The Preservation of Natural Beauty" (1964). One member of that task force was William H. Whyte.
  - Canada, 1962 October 11-November 5 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe (2/24-25/1971) -- "Implications of Certain European-Based Activities and Interests for Ford Foundation Objectives in Asia and the Pacific", 1971 February 24-25 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe (2/24-25/1971) -- "Memorandum on the Foundation's Interest and Work in Education and Research in Europe," "Public Education Program Interests," and "Activities of Higher Education" (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe (2/24-25/1971) -- "Middle East and Africa (MEA) Interest in Europe" (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe (2/24-25/1971) -- "National Affairs' International Activities" (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe (2/24-25/1971) -- "Notes on Latin American Interest and Activity in Europe" (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - "Ford Foundation Grants and Projects in the Study of Philanthropy", 1964 April 15 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Individual Grants and Tax Consequences, 1969 August 11-1970 April 24 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - International Affairs (IA) Cultural Grants Transferred to Division of Humanities and Arts, 1966 October 4-1967 January 4 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Jesuit Padre Harbrecht to Heald Re: "New Foundations", 1964 October-November 9 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Population Grants in Europe, 1971 February (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Research Project on Attitudes Toward the Foundation and Ford Cars and Public Opinion Poll, 1963 December 3-1964 July 27 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Staff Memoranda -- Federal Tax Exemption Rules, 1960 October 26-1963 October 10 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Staff Memoranda -- Instructions for Grant Preparation, 1958 November 11-1961 November 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Staff Memoranda -- Miscellaneous, 1962 - 1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Staff Memoranda -- Overseas Grants Tax Exemptions, 1960 October 24-December 22 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Staff Memoranda -- Travel Arrangements, 1960 March 24- 1964 May 14 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Staff Memoranda -- Staff Appointments, 1963 April 4- 1964 September 25 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Statistical Report on Program Action Disposition, 1963 September 26-October 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Admin -- Administration Plans for 1966, 1965 April 16-May 3 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Education -- Educational Facilities Lab, 1965 January 22-August 6 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Education -- General, 1965 February 4-1966 June 13 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Education -- Vocational Education -- General, 1962 April 23-October 31 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Education -- Report on Vocational Education as a Field for Ford Foundation Activity, 1962 September 4 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Economic Development Administration -- Evaluations -- General, 1959 February 16-1961 August 17 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Economic Development Administration -- Evaluation of the Joint Council on Economic Education, 1961 May (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Economic Development Administration -- Evaluation of the Economics Institute, 1961 July 31 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Economic Development Administration -- Evaluation of Fellowship Programs in Business Administration and Economics, 1962 February 15 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Economic Development Administration -- Grant Requests, 1963 February 15-1966 August 24 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Economic Development Administration -- General, 1964 November 18-1966 July 7 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Economic Development Administration -- Policy Discussion Paper, 1965 January 15 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1954 April (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Humanities and the Arts (HA) -- Educational Television, 1955 November 17 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - HA -- Social Position of Artist and His Institutions, 1958 April 8 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - HA -- Inquiry into the Support of Arts in France, UK, Denmark and Italy, 1958 July 2-August 11 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - HA -- "An Enlarged Program in the Arts", 1960 March (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - HA -- Edward F. D'Arms, Warsaw Trip, Polish Team (1 of 2), 1961 January 5-February 13 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - HA -- Edward F. D'Arms, Warsaw Trip, Polish Team (2 of 2), 1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - HA -- Edward F. D'Arms Staff Trip to Yugoslavia, 1968 February (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - HA -- "The Arts and The Ford Foundation: 1969", 1968 December (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - HA -- General, 1962 December 2-1966 August 19 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - HA -- Neiman Fellows, Harvard, 1964 December 18-1966 February 21 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - HA -- India/Asia, 1967 October 17-1968 February 12 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - HA -- New York Planning Commission, 1967 November 30-1968 February 8 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - HA -- European Activities, 1967 December 29-1968 March 21 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - HA -- "Government Policy in the Arts", 1968 August (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - HA -- "Ford Foundation Strategy in the Arts - A Review", 1968 November 19 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - HA -- European Luncheon Club, 1969 September 17 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - HA -- Subcommittee Meeting, Board Meeting, 1969 December 16- 1970 March 5 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - HA -- Grant Requests (1 of 3), 1972 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - HA -- Grant Requests (2 of 3), 1972 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - HA -- Grant Requests (3 of 3), 1972 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - International Affairs (IA) -- Humanities and the Arts (HA) Relations, 1957 January 29-1958 February 24 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - IA -- "An Independent Report on the Graduate School of Public Administration at the University of Bologna" by James Watson & Guglielmo Negri, 1960 March (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - IA -- Institute for Research and Publications Madrid Meeting, 1962 March 15-June 25 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - IA -- Svimez Evaluation, 1962 April 13-1962 December 9 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - IA -- "Report to the Ford Foundation International Affairs Program on the Free University Berlin and the West German Universities" by Sigmund Neumann, 1962 July 17 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - IA -- Evaluation -- General, 1962 August 21 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - IA -- Grant Request Items, 1962 October 8-1966 August 16 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - IA -- "Foreign Affairs and Mass Media: (U.S. Public Understanding of World Affairs)" by Theodore Kaghan, 1963 January 4 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - IA -- Report on Graduate Institute of International Studies at Geneva by Philip E. Mosely, 1963 February 1 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - IA -- "Strengthening the Comprehensive Development of the Atlantic Partnership", 1963 March (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - IA -- "Strengthening the Comprehensive Development of the Atlantic Partnership" Discussion Paper, 1963 March 18 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - IA -- General, 1963 March 22-1966 September 14 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - IA -- Citizen's Education in World Affairs (1 of 2), 1964 January 28-1965 December 28 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - IA -- Citizen's Education in World Affairs (2 of 2), 1964 September 28-December 22 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - IA -- Citizen's Education in World Affairs -- Robert Tucker's Notes, 1964 December (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - IA -- "International Affairs Discussion Paper: Review of International Affairs-Supported Conferences and Meetings", 1964 May 27 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - IA -- "Report on Committee on Citizen Education in World Affairs", 1965 February 15 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - IA -- United Nations Association -- Memoranda, 1965 December 16-1966 January 17 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - IA -- Rapprochement -- Correspondence, Memoranda, 1966 June 18-September 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)